<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-03-12T15:48:13+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Geo Imagine Developer</title><subtitle>script your own Earth</subtitle><entry><title type="html">An expert system model for mapping tropical wetlands and peatlands reveals South America as the largest contributor.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/journal/gbc-pantropical-wetlands/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An expert system model for mapping tropical wetlands and peatlands reveals South America as the largest contributor." /><published>2017-05-09T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-05-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/journal/gbc-pantropical-wetlands</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/journal/gbc-pantropical-wetlands/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.13689&quot;&gt;Gumbricht, T., Roman-Cuesta, R. M., Verchot, L., Herold, M., Wittmann, F., Householder, E., Herold, N. and Murdiyarso, D. (2017), An expert system model for mapping tropical wetlands and peatlands reveals South America as the largest contributor. Global Change Biology, 23, 3581–3599.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 class=&quot;foot-description&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wetlands are important providers of ecosystem services and key regulators of climate change. They positively contribute to global warming through their greenhouse gas emissions, and negatively through the accumulation of organic material in histosols, particularly in peatlands. Our understanding of wetlands’ services is currently constrained by limited knowledge on their distribution, extent, volume, interannual flood variability and disturbance levels. We present an expert system approach to estimate wetland and peatland areas, depths and volumes, which relies on three biophysical indices related to wetland and peat formation: (1) long-term water supply exceeding atmospheric water demand; (2) annually or seasonally water-logged soils; and (3) a geomorphological position where water is supplied and retained. Tropical and subtropical wetlands estimates reach 4.7 million km2 (Mkm2). In line with current understanding, the American continent is the major contributor (45%), and Brazil, with its Amazonian interfluvial region, contains the largest tropical wetland area (800,720 km2). Our model suggests, however, unprecedented extents and volumes of peatland in the tropics (1.7 Mkm2 and 7,268 (6,076–7,368) km3), which more than threefold current estimates. Unlike current understanding, our estimates suggest that South America and not Asia contributes the most to tropical peatland area and volume (ca. 44% for both) partly related to some yet unaccounted extended deep deposits but mainly to extended but shallow peat in the Amazon Basin. Brazil leads the peatland area and volume contribution. Asia hosts 38% of both tropical peat area and volume with Indonesia as the main regional contributor and still the holder of the deepest and most extended peat areas in the tropics. Africa hosts more peat than previously reported but climatic and topographic contexts leave it as the least peat-forming continent. Our results suggest large biases in our current understanding of the distribution, area and volumes of tropical peat and their continental contributions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Gumbricht, T., Roman-Cuesta, R. M., Verchot, L., Herold, M., Wittmann, F., Householder, E., Herold, N. and Murdiyarso, D. (2017), An expert system model for mapping tropical wetlands and peatlands reveals South America as the largest contributor. Global Change Biology, 23, 3581–3599.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Soil Moisture Dynamics Estimated from MODIS Time Series Images.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/refereechapter/book-twi-timeseries/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Soil Moisture Dynamics Estimated from MODIS Time Series Images." /><published>2016-11-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-11-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/refereechapter/book-twi-timeseries</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/refereechapter/book-twi-timeseries/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-47037-5_12&quot;&gt;Gumbricht, T. (2015). Soil Moisture Dynamics Estimated from MODIS Time Series Images. In Y. Ban (Ed.), Multitemporal Remote Sensing (pp. 233–253). Springer. DOI :10.1007/978-3-319- 47037-5_12.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 class=&quot;foot-description&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The annual cyclic phenomena of soil surface wetness influences for in- stance vegetation growth, drought, flooding, and soil properties. This study presents an attempt to define metrics relevant for capturing the soil moisture dynamics from an annual series of wetness estimates derived from global Moderate-resolution imaging spectroradiometer (MODIS) images. Different algorithms for both smooth- ing and gap-filling the time series are tested with the results compared to in-situ data. Neither the smoothing nor the gap-filling improve the capturing of the surface wet- ness phenology compared to using unsmoothed time series data. The smoothing, however removes the effects of erratic rainfall events and noise, and the smoothed time series was considered more robust for identification of wetness phenology. Metrics capturing the global surface wetness phenology for 2011, extracted after smoothing using a simplified locally weighted scatterplot smoothing (LOWESS) model, are presented at a spatial resolution of 500 m for the calendar year 2011.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Gumbricht, T. (2015). Soil Moisture Dynamics Estimated from MODIS Time Series Images. In Y. Ban (Ed.), Multitemporal Remote Sensing (pp. 233–253). Springer. DOI :10.1007/978-3-319- 47037-5_12.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mapping of soil properties and land degradation risk in Africa using MODIS reflectance.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/journal/geoderma-africa-soil/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mapping of soil properties and land degradation risk in Africa using MODIS reflectance." /><published>2016-02-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-02-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/journal/geoderma-africa-soil</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/journal/geoderma-africa-soil/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.geoderma.2015.06.023&quot;&gt;Vågen, T.-G., Winowiecki, L. A., Tondoh, J. E., Desta, L. T., &amp;amp; Gumbricht, T. (2016). Mapping of soil properties and land degradation risk in Africa using MODIS reflectance. Geoderma, 263, 216–225.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 class=&quot;foot-description&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a need for up-to-date assessments and maps of soil properties and land health at scales relevant for decision-making and management, including for properties that are dynamic and hence change in response to management. Also, there is a need for approaches to soil mapping that capture the ever increasing effects that humans are having on the environment in general and specifically on soil properties worldwide. In this paper, we develop models for digital soil mapping based on remote sensing data from the Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer (MODIS) platform for Africa. The article presents maps of soil organic carbon (SOC), pH, sand and sum of exchangeable bases, as well as prevalence of root-depth restrictions in the upper 50 cm of the soil profile. Prediction models were developed based on spatially balanced field survey data, representing all major climate zones on the continent. The prediction models for soil property mapping performed well, with overall RMSEP values of 10.6, 0.34, 9.1, and 6.5 for SOC, pH, sand, and sum of bases, respectively. The accuracy of the prediction model for root-depth restrictions was 77%, with an AUC of 0.85 and Cohen’s kappa value of 0.52 when averaged across predictions run on independent test data. The methods and maps developed can provide much improved identification of soil and land health constraints, and spatial targeting of land management interventions at various scales, informing both policy and practice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Vågen, T.-G., Winowiecki, L. A., Tondoh, J. E., Desta, L. T., &amp;amp; Gumbricht, T. (2016). Mapping of soil properties and land degradation risk in Africa using MODIS reflectance. Geoderma, 263, 216–225.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hybrid Mapping of pantropical wetlands from optical satellite images, hydrology and geomorphology.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/refereechapter/book-pantropical-wetlands/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hybrid Mapping of pantropical wetlands from optical satellite images, hydrology and geomorphology." /><published>2015-10-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-10-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/refereechapter/book-pantropical-wetlands</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/refereechapter/book-pantropical-wetlands/">&lt;p&gt;Gumbricht, T. (2015). Hybrid Mapping of pantropical wetlands from optical satellite images, hydrology and geomorphology. In R. W. Tiner, M. W. Lang, &amp;amp; V. Klemas (Eds.), Advances in Wetland Classification and Mapping (pp. 435–454). Boca Raton: CRC press; Taylor and Francis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Gumbricht, T. (2015). Hybrid Mapping of pantropical wetlands from optical satellite images, hydrology and geomorphology. In R. W. Tiner, M. W. Lang, &amp;amp; V. Klemas (Eds.), Advances in Wetland Classification and Mapping (pp. 435–454). Boca Raton: CRC press; Taylor and Francis.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mapping global tropical wetlands from earth observing satellite imagery.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/report/report-wetland-mapping/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mapping global tropical wetlands from earth observing satellite imagery." /><published>2012-08-22T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2012-08-22T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/report/report-wetland-mapping</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/report/report-wetland-mapping/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cifor.org/publications/pdf_files/WPapers/WP103CIFOR.pdf&quot;&gt;Gumbricht, T. (2012). Mapping global tropical wetlands from earth observing satellite imagery (Working Paper 103)., CIFOR, Bogor.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 class=&quot;foot-description&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wetlands have a high biodiversity, and are key
regulators of the flow of water and the fluxes of
mineral and nutrients from land to sea. Wetlands
only cover a few percent of the global land surface,
but their soils contain as much carbon as the entire
biosphere. Yet the extent, volume and carbon content
of the world’s wetlands are not accurately known,
in particular, for tropical and sub-tropical regions.
Despite their importance, wetlands have historically
been regarded as wastelands, and have largely been
ignored in studies of climate change. Improved maps
of the distribution of global tropical wetlands, their
volumes and carbon contents are urgently needed.
Because wetlands are characterised by their water,
soil and vegetation conditions, they are difficult to
identify from satellite images of earth. Few of the
existing efforts at mapping the global land surface
have attempted to identify wetlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wetlands exclusively occur under certain topographic
conditions, and where the soil and water conditions
are such that inundation can, and actually does,
occur on a regular (annual) basis. Taking this as
a starting point, a set of novel indexes relating to
wetlands was developed. The first index is a climatic
topographic wetness index. Using a global digital
elevation model, combined with global climate
data, a tropical global map of surface wetness was created. Using global optical satellite images from
the moderate resolution imaging spectroradiometer
(MODIS) a second wetness index was developed.
Compared to previous satellite-based wetness indexes,
the index attempts to remove the vegetation influence
and focus on the soil surface wetness. From an
annual time-series of MODIS images, the inundation
cycle of the global tropics was captured. The two
wetness indexes are strong candidates for mapping
the distribution of global tropical wetlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional image classification is based on reference
data, and usually attempts to delineate features
from a single image. As wetlands are characterised
by annual variations in inundation, an approach
for classifying wetlands from a chrono-sequence
of annual MODIS images was developed. In the
chrono-sequence, only locations with similar
climatic seasonality, and within spatial proximity
were classified based on a reference site. Wetlands,
often with vegetation and wetness phenology out
of phase compared to adjacent dry lands, can thus
be delineated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initial results are promising for all approaches
developed in this study; however, lack of reference
sites and reference data has hitherto prevented the
development of a global tropical wetland map.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Gumbricht, T. (2012). Mapping global tropical wetlands from earth observing satellite imagery (Working Paper 103)., CIFOR, Bogor.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Land Health Surveillance: An Evidence-Based Approach to Land Ecosystem Management.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/report/report-land-health/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Land Health Surveillance: An Evidence-Based Approach to Land Ecosystem Management." /><published>2012-08-22T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2012-08-22T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/report/report-land-health</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/report/report-land-health/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.unep.org/dewa/Portals/67/pdf/LHS_Report_lowres.pdf&quot;&gt;UNEP (2012). Land Health Surveillance: An Evidence-Based Approach to Land Ecosystem Management. Illustrated with a Case Study in the West Africa Sahel. Nairobi: UNEP. Contributors Shepherd, K., Gumbricht, T., Shepherd G. , Vågen, T.-G. &amp;amp; Walsh M. G.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">UNEP (2012). Land Health Surveillance: An Evidence-Based Approach to Land Ecosystem Management. Illustrated with a Case Study in the West Africa Sahel. Nairobi: UNEP. Contributors Shepherd, K., Gumbricht, T., Shepherd G. , Vågen, T.-G. &amp;amp; Walsh M. G.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Do ecosystem services influence household wealth in rural Mali?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/journal/ecolecon-rural-Mali/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do ecosystem services influence household wealth in rural Mali?" /><published>2012-08-22T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2012-08-22T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/journal/ecolecon-rural-Mali</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/journal/ecolecon-rural-Mali/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecolecon.2012.08.005&quot;&gt;Liebenow, D. K., Cohen, M. J., Gumbricht, T., Shepherd, K. D., &amp;amp; Shepherd, G. (2012). Do ecosystem services influence household wealth in rural Mali? Ecological Economics, 82, 33– 44.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 class=&quot;foot-description&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impact of ecosystem services on human livelihood is rarely demonstrated. We investigated whether ecosystem services influence household wealth in semi-arid rural Mali, where climate variability and soil degradation were expected to regulate subsistence production. Mean rainfall, mean rain use efficiency, and rain use efficiency trends (a land degradation proxy) over the last 25 years were used to quantify ecosystem services. Asset wealth was measured in 2527 households from 65 villages spanning the range in ecosystem services. We evaluated effects on wealth, controlling for household size and demographics, ethnicity, village size, crop selection, and distance to open water and markets. While wealth variation was dominated by demographics, significant associations with ecosystem services were observed. Predicted household wealth increased significantly (20%) with rainfall. Effects of rain use efficiency mean and trends were also significant, but only when conditioned on rainfall. With lower rainfall, wealth increased with mean rain use efficiency (+ 33%) but decreased with rain use efficiency trend (− 22%). With higher rainfall, however, wealth decreased with rain use efficiency (− 57%) and increased markedly with rain use efficiency trend (+ 185%). While ecosystem services are clearly important, their effect on rural poverty is complex and potentially obscured by coping strategies that mitigate environmental limitations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Liebenow, D. K., Cohen, M. J., Gumbricht, T., Shepherd, K. D., &amp;amp; Shepherd, G. (2012). Do ecosystem services influence household wealth in rural Mali? Ecological Economics, 82, 33– 44.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sahel Atlas of Changing Landscapes: Tracing trends and variations in vegetation cover and soil condition.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/atlas/atlas-sahel/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sahel Atlas of Changing Landscapes: Tracing trends and variations in vegetation cover and soil condition." /><published>2012-08-22T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2012-08-22T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/atlas/atlas-sahel</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/atlas/atlas-sahel/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.unep.org/dewa/Portals/67/pdf/Sahel_Atlas_lowres.pdf&quot;&gt;Vågen, T and T. Gumbricht (2012). Sahel Atlas of Changing Landscapes: Tracing trends and variations in vegetation cover and soil condition. Nairobi: UNEP.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Vågen, T and T. Gumbricht (2012). Sahel Atlas of Changing Landscapes: Tracing trends and variations in vegetation cover and soil condition. Nairobi: UNEP.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Land Health Surveillance for Targeting Climate Change and Ecosystem Management Interventions in Africa. Final Report.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/report/report-UNEP/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Land Health Surveillance for Targeting Climate Change and Ecosystem Management Interventions in Africa. Final Report." /><published>2010-08-17T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2010-08-17T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/report/report-UNEP</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/report/report-UNEP/">&lt;p&gt;Gumbricht, T. (2010). Final Report Land Health Surveillance for Targeting Climate Change and Ecosystem Management Interventions in Africa with Emphasis on Pilot One UN Countries: Mozambique, Tanzania and Rwanda. Nairobi, World Agroforestry Center (ICRAF). 67 p.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Gumbricht, T. (2010). Final Report Land Health Surveillance for Targeting Climate Change and Ecosystem Management Interventions in Africa with Emphasis on Pilot One UN Countries: Mozambique, Tanzania and Rwanda. Nairobi, World Agroforestry Center (ICRAF). 67 p.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Land Health Surveillance for Targeting Climate Change and Ecosystem Management Interventions in Africa. Methods</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/report/report-UNEP/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Land Health Surveillance for Targeting Climate Change and Ecosystem Management Interventions in Africa. Methods" /><published>2009-08-17T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-08-17T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/report/report-UNEP</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/report/report-UNEP/">&lt;p&gt;Gumbricht, T. (2009). Land Health Surveillance for Targeting Climate Change and Ecosystem Management Interventions in Africa with Emphasis on Pilot One UN Countries: Mozambique, Tanzania and Rwanda. Nairobi. World Agroforestry Center (ICRAF). 44 p.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Gumbricht, T. (2009). Land Health Surveillance for Targeting Climate Change and Ecosystem Management Interventions in Africa with Emphasis on Pilot One UN Countries: Mozambique, Tanzania and Rwanda. Nairobi. World Agroforestry Center (ICRAF). 44 p.</summary></entry></feed>